All right. So, ITGN is the דף daf that we start the
משנה mishna בר-מעיין בן חוה-זה. bar-ma'ayan ben chava-zeh. And we're dealing with
walls and now we're about to see ditches between courtyards and what
allows the courtyards to be one if they want, what requires them
to be two, and what situations must they be one, is it
not considered a divider at all? So, משנה. mishna. חריץ שבין שתי
חצרות, charitz shebein shtei chatzerot, if you have a ditch between two
yards,
עמוק עשרה ורוחב ארבעה, amok asara ve'rochav arba, so it's the reverse
of the wall, it's ten deep and it is four
wide. Now the wall, even if it's not wide at all, is
a divider. The whole issue about the wall being four wide was
to make it a separate domain and carrying from the wall to
the חצר chatzer vice versa. A ditch, however, if it's not four
wide is not a divider because then you just step over. But
once it's four wide, like a foot wide, then it serves as
a divider. Okay, so מערבין שתים ואין מערבין אחת. me'arvin shtayim ve'ein
me'arvin achat. Then it serves as a wall and you have to
make two separate courts, each courtyard has to be separate for an
עירוב, eruv, they cannot be one. אפילו מלא קש או תבן, afilu
malei kash o teven, even if it's filled with straw or stubble,
that's not considered to fill it up and it's still considered that's
only temporary and it's still considered essentially to be a divider. Even
if right now you could step over it because it's filled, that
does not matter. Well, for water, that would even be more so,
you can't step into the water, you'd fall in. What if it's
filled with snow? That's an interesting... anyway, or iced over. But presumably,
if it's not, if it's very temporary, you look at what its
basic configuration is, not at what it currently is. אפילו מלא קש
או תבן. afilu malei kash o teven. מלא עפר או צרורות, malei
afar o tzerorot, however, if it's filled with dirt or with rocks,
pebbles, מערבין אחת ואין מערבין שתים, me'arvin achat ve'ein me'arvin shtayim, then
you don't have the option of going the other way. Then it's
basically just fine, there's no ditch here so it's one big courtyard.
Right, by a wall with a door in it or a window
in it, you can choose to consider that separate or to consider
it access and one. Here it's all or the, all one or
all the other. If it's a real ditch they're separate, if it's
a ditch that's filled they're combined. ונתן עליו
נסר,
v'notan
alav neser, here is a counterpart. ונתן עליו נסר שרוחב ארבעה
טפחים, v'notan alav neser sherohav arba'a tefachim, you put a plank across
this ditch that's ארבעה טפחים arba'a tefachim wide, it's about a foot
wide, okay? So the ditch itself is only a, right, the ditch
itself is only a foot wide, but the point of the, if
this is your ditch here, right, the point is that your plank
is a foot wide so it's wide enough for you to walk,
right? The ditch is a minimal foot gap, the ditch could be,
I don't know, twenty feet apart, okay? But the plank, for the
plank to connect the two edges of the ditch, right, the plank
has to be four wide for you to walk and for it
to be a safe way to walk across the ditch. Okay, so
you've got this plank that is four wide.
וכן שתי גזוזטראות זו כנגד זו, vechen shtei gezuztraot zu keneged zu,
or let's say you've got the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, I'll
tell you the way רש"י Rashi reads it. You've got two balconies
that overlook one another in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, now
forget the ditch. If you try to walk over the balcony, they're
their own ditch, you try to step from one balcony to the
next you fall down to the ground. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says
what it means is that if these two balconies are less than
ארבעה טפחים arba'a tefachim apart, the same way if the ditch is
narrower than ארבעה טפחים, arba'a tefachim, it's not considered a ditch, you
just step over it. If the two balconies are less than ארבעה
טפחים arba'a tefachim apart also they're not considered separate, they're considered connected,
you can just step over it. Okay, רש"י Rashi says that this,
the two balconies is referring to the case of the plank. You
have two balconies that are far apart, if you put a plank
across them that gives you the option of connecting them. We'll see
why תוספות Tosafot reads it the way he does later in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, מערבין שתים ואם רצה מערבין אחת. me'arvin shtayim ve'im
ratza me'arvin achat.
So in this case you can do, you have the option of
two or one. So basically if the ditch is completely, is a
foot wide and it's ארבעה טפחים arba'a tefachim wide and there's nothing
in it or only straw, whatever, then it's completely a separation, they're
definitely two. If it's really filled with dirt then it's nothing, they're
one. What's the case where you have the option of combining them
as one? Similar to a door in a wall. What's similar to
a door in a wall? A plank across the ditch. So if
you have a plank across the ditch you can choose to make
it considered one because you have access. Yes or because you still
got the ditch there you can define them as two.
תוספות Tosfos says what the משנה Mishna is also saying is if
the ditch is less than four טפחים. Tefachim. If it's ten טפחים
Tefachim deep but less than four טפחים Tefachim wide so that also
gives you the option of going either way. You can choose to
call them two cause it's got a ditch you can choose to
call them one because if you want you could step over it
and that's the case also תוספות Tosfos says of the two of
the two balconies that they're less than four טפחים Tefachim apart so
you can choose to make them two you can choose to make
them one. פחות מכאן Pachos mikan and again if the ditch is
now this is what I just said.
Oh if not the ditch if the plank is less than four
טפחים Tefachim wide so it's not really considered traversable it's a very
thin narrow plank then מערבין שנים ואין מערבין אחד. mearvin shnayim veein
mearvin echad. Then the plank does nothing and therefore you have to
make them separate. So you need the plank to be a certain
width if it's not it's worthless. So if you've got a ditch
with a plank or like תוספות Tosfos also says if you have
a ditch but it's not a big gap it's only it's less
than four טפחים Tefachim from one side of the other then you
can choose to make them two or choose to make them one.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara
starts with the idea about the straw and the stubble. תבן לא
חוצץ? Teven lo chaitz? Are you telling me that straw does not
make a divider meaning straw's considered essentially like not present it doesn't
fill up the ditch? והא אנן תנן Veha'an'tenan we're going to teach
it's the next משנה Mishna we're going to learn today
והא אנן
תנן veha'an'tenan מצבין שבין שתי חצרות matzbein shebein shtei chatzeirot if you
have basically a pile of תבן teven מצבין matzbein from the word
תבן teven a big pile of straw which is like a big
mound ten טפחים Tefachim high a wall out of straw which is
between the two courtyards גבוה עשרה טפחים gavoha asara Tefachim מערבין שנים
ואין מערבין אחד mearvin shnayim veein mearvin echad that defines the two
courtyards as separate. So why is it different why to make a
wall does straw count but to fill up a ditch straw doesn't
count either it's considered a real presence or it's not a real
presence?
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי Amar Abaye says אביי Abaye
לענין מחיצה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דהויא מחיצה. leinyan mechitza kulei alma
lo peligi dehavya mechitza. When it comes to making a מחיצה mechitza
everybody agrees it constitutes a
מחיצה. mechitza. אבל לענין חציצה Aval leinyan chatzitza but to fill to
be like a you know an obstruction essentially to fill up a
hole in the ground to fill up the ditch אי בטליה חוצץ
iy batlei chaitz if you sort of negate it there designate that
it's going to remain there then
then it's it's it stops it up it's considered to fill the
ditch ואי לא בטליה לא חוצץ veiy lo batlei lo chaitz and
if you did not negate it there לא חוצץ lo chaitz it
does not fill up the ditch. So we're going to see about
being מבטל mevatel it in a minute that's what the גמרא Gemara
is about to discuss because the משנה Mishna doesn't mention that the
משנה Mishna says the straw never does anything but the גמרא Gemara
was about to discuss that if you basically say I'm leaving the
straw there permanently it's made to fill up the ditch then it
does have an effect. But less than that not so אביי's Abaye
basic answer is is he doesn't say so what's the difference why
does it make a wall
and not fill up a ditch? It does when it comes to
make a wall everybody agrees it makes a wall when it comes
to fill up a ditch it doesn't fill up a ditch which
is a little funny it sort of begs the question but the
basic point I would say is being is is that you know
is that if you've got the ditch that's your basic like configuration
the basic the permanent structure here is a ditch right is something
that separates so in order to like change that configuration to remove
the presence of the ditch you need something a little bit more
permanent because you start with the given is you've got a ditch
and they're divided whereas so to change that you need a more
something permanent presence in the ditch or else you just look at
it as a ditch filled with straw whereas by the case of
the wall even if the the straw is not permanent there and
it's more transitory right now at least you have a wall it's
not fighting against the presence and coming to redefine the presence of
something else. That seems to be what the what this point is
or you could just say there's a lower standard the standard of
what you require for מחיצה mechitza is less right maybe it's easy
to make a מחיצה mechitza it's harder to make something that actually
changes the something's configuration. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says the
following
מלאי עפר Malei afar so now if it's filled with dirt then
it does obviously make it a non-ditch. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואפילו בסתמא va'afilu bistama you mean to tell me if it's filled
with dirt even without any special designation just סתם stam you know
even in a default case filled with dirt changes it והא תנן
veha'tnan we taught in a משנה Mishna בית שמלאוהו תבן או צרורות
bayis shemiluhu teven o tzerorot if you have a house that you
filled with straw or with rocks וביטלו בטל uvitlo batel if you
negated the straw there you basically said I am leaving the straw
in this house permanently I don't know why but okay I'm boarding
up this house and I'm keeping it with straw then it's בטל
batel and it's considered to change the configuration of the house. Now
why is that important because you happen to have a dead body
in the house now if you've got a טפח tefach between the
body and the roof the טומאה tuma stops at the roof and
spreads throughout the house if however you fill The body was buried
in the house, it was totally
under—anybody ever see Witness? Remember how when he pulls the grain and
gets totally buried? No, nobody knows that? That's from twenty years ago.
That was a good movie. Anyway,
if it's totally buried under all of this straw, then it's buried
in the ground, and then there's no roof because there's nothing between
the body and everything is totally filled. So then the טומאה tumah
goes through the roof. Okay, there's no roof effectively. So if you
plan on leaving the straw there, then it changes the configuration and
then the טומאה tumah will not hit the roof and spread but
will go straight through.
ביטלו ובטל. Bitlo u-vattel. So the גמרא Gemara says ביטלו אין, bitlo
in, if you were מבטל mevatel it, you basically said you planned
on leaving it there forever, yes, then that makes a difference when
it's filled
with—אין, in, לא ביטלו לא. lo bitlo lo. If you weren't מבטל
mevatel no, and this includes צרורות, tzerorot, rocks. So you see here
that rocks you have to do ביטול, bitul, rocks by themselves filling
a house with rocks don't just naturally change the configuration. So okay,
that's the question. Maybe there are different standards, but at least on
the face of it, it contradicts the משנה Mishnah that says that
simply dirt makes it different. Dirt or rocks makes it different by
itself.
אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna seventy-nine עמוד א, amud aleph, says
רב הונא, Rav Huna, מאן תנא אהלות רבי יוסי היא. man tanna
Oholot Rabbi Yose hi. That's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Okay, which רבי
יוסי? Rabbi Yose? We're about to see in a minute. So the
גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אי רבי יוסי איפכא שמעינן ליה. ee
Rabbi Yose ipcha shaminnan leh. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the opposite.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose doesn't help your problem. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
is the one that demands more, not less. He's the author of
the משנה Mishnah who says you don't need—that, I'm sorry. He says
the author of the משנה Mishnah that you need ביטול bitul is
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. I'm sorry, I said it the wrong way.
So he was saying רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose demands more. For רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose it's not just enough to have dirt, you need
ביטול. bitul. גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean? The opposite is
true. We see that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose demands less. דתניא De-tanya
we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yose omer:
תבן דאין עשוי לפנותו, teven de-ein asuy le-pnoto, if you have תבן
teven there which you are not intending to remove, meaning you have
תבן teven that you plan to be there forever, that's your intention.
I don't know why you would do that, but that's your intention.
הרי הוא כסתם עפר, Harei hu ke-stam afar, that's like עפר, afar,
non-specified עפר, afar, ובטל, u-vattel, and it's בטל batel and it changes
the configuration. Similarly, עפר ועשוי לפנותו, afar ve-asuy le-pnoto,
the reverse, if you have עפר afar which you plan on removing,
הרי הוא כסתם תבן, harei hu ke-stam teven, that's like תבן teven
without any particular designation, ולא בטל, ve-lo battel, and it's not בטל.
batel. It's a very nice way of remembering it because basically what's
the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha is עפר afar by itself is
considered בטל, batel, you don't need to designate it. תבן, teven, if
you just have תבן teven there, you assume it's going to be
removed and it doesn't change the landscape. But if you're מבטל mevatel
the תבן, teven, then it does change the landscape. So רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose says by תבן teven it matters if you're מבטל mevatel
it or not. By עפר, afar, unless you explicitly plan on removing
the עפר, afar, even if—so right, there's always three statuses. There's you
don't have anything particular in mind, you plan on leaving it בטל,
batel, or you plan on removing it עשוי לפנותו. asuy le-pnoto. So
he basically says עפר afar if it's סתם stam or obviously if
you're מבטל mevatel it, it changes the configuration. The only time it's
not considered to change the setup is if you plan on removing
it.
Okay. תבן, teven, however, he says only changes the configuration in that
last quadrant when you're planning on leaving it there. Anything else, the
סתם stam case of תבן teven is not. So that's רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yose. Now that is completely consistent with our משנה. Mishnah. Our
משנה Mishnah says that the—is a סתם stam case, you didn't plan
on doing one thing or the other, and it says the תבן
teven doesn't change the landscape and the עפר afar does.
Okay. So that's—our משנה Mishnah is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, works well.
But the גמרא Gemara said רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the author
of אהלות Oholot that says you always need ביטול. bitul. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב אסי. ela amar Rav Assi. So
רב אסי Rav Assi says fine, I got it reversed. You got
it reversed. Here's the way it should be. מאן תנא עירובין, Man
tanna Eruvin, who's the author of our משנה Mishnah in עירובין? Eruvin?
רבי יוסי היא. Rabbi Yose hi. That's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Okay.
So again, here's the problem. Our משנה Mishnah says that you have
nothing particular in mind, תבן teven doesn't change the landscape, עפר afar
does. In אהלות Oholot we say that even עפר afar you need
to do ביטול. bitul. So the גמרא's Gemara saying fine, that's a
different opinion. Our משנה Mishnah is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose says עפר afar you don't have to do ביטול, bitul,
the author in the משנה Mishnah אהלות Oholot is a different opinion.
All right. By the way, תוספות Tosafot points out that what this
shows is that they knew that the answer to the problem of
the אהלות Oholot עירובין Eruvin contradiction was רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but
they just got it wrong. At first they said oh, I know
there's a רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose here that makes a difference, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose is the author of אהלות. Oholot. No, no, no,
that's the opposite. Okay, fine, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the author
of עירובין. Eruvin. No, but they had a tradi—they remembered, they remembered
that one of them was רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, they just got
it wrong which was which. Okay, yes.
I'm assuming that whatever you've ביטל bitulled at the time of when
שבת Shabbat comes in, it remains that status throughout שבת. Shabbat.
But what if somebody just
happens to remove it? Excellent question.
Even if he changes his intention?
We're going to see it in a minute. We're going to see
it in a minute. Now intention won't matter, but once it was
defined, but if the actual physical reality changes, we'll see it. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
אומר, Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua omer, which is Michael's answer: טומאה
שבת כרמיתי? Tuma Shabbat karamsi? Forget saying it's a debate of תנאים
Tannaim that sometimes according to one תנא Tanna you need ביטול, bitul,
according to the other you don't. There are different halachic categories. One
is טומאה, Tuma, one is שבת. Shabbat. הנהו איסור שבת, Hanakh issur
Shabbat, now why is שבת, Shabbat, why do you not need ביטול
bitul by שבת Shabbat for the dirt? It says a very obvious
reason. You're never going to remove the dirt on שבת. Shabbat. Why
wouldn't you remove the dirt on שבת? Shabbat? It's מוקצה. muktsa. Okay,
הנהו איסור שבת אפילו ארנקי נמי מבטל אינשי. Hanakh issur Shabbat afilu
arneki nami mivattel inshi. Even a wallet you would leave there. Normally
you would never leave your wallet anywhere, right? But on שבת Shabbat
if your wallet happened to be in the dirt, you're not going
to remove it on שבת Shabbat because it's שבת, Shabbat, it's מוקצה.
muktsa. So he says look, even if normally to change the landscape
you need to do ביטול bitul on dirt, dirt doesn't do it
by itself is which is what we see according to one תנא
Tanna in ערלות, Orlos, by שבת Shabbat it's considered מבטל- mivattel it's
considered בטל battel because you're gonna leave it there. רב אשי אמר
בית וחריץ כרמיתי? Rav Ashi amar bayis vakharitz karamsi? Now this takes
as is a similar to the answer before about the difference between
a ditch and a wall. That it's not about whether it's שבת
Shabbat versus ערלות, Orlos, but it's about whether what type of configuration
we're talking about. One is a house and one is a ditch.
So he says בשלמא חריץ לאטומי
קאתי. Bishlama kharitz limitamei khei. By a ditch, what do you do
with a ditch? You fill a ditch. Okay, a ditch can naturally
be even if it's there for a purpose, a natural thing to
do with it is to fill it and get it back to
level ground. So if you have dirt in a ditch, we're gonna
naturally say you now have level ground, you don't have a ditch
anymore. אבל בית אלא בית לאטומי
קאתי? But bayis ella bayis limitamei khei? Do you normally fill a
house and leave it that way? You might store, right, you might
store straw there, but who's gonna leave straw there? And even if
it's dirt, who's gonna leave dirt in a house? Now it's not
that it'll never happen, so if you have an intention to leave
it there, fine. But if you ask what is the default way
I should look at this case, dirt in a ditch I should
look at it as it's no longer a ditch. Dirt in a
house, it's still a house, unless you are intentionally want to leave
it there because you assume the dirt will be removed. So there's
a lot of ways of distinguishing between those two cases. Now to
the case of the plank along the- along the ditch. נתן עליו
נסר שרחבו ארבע. Nasan alav neser she-rochav arba. You put a plank
that goes from one end of the ditch to the other, could
be ten feet apart, but the plank itself has to be ארבע
arba טפחים tefakhim like a foot wide to be considered traversable. אמר
רבא לא שנו
אלא שנתן לרחבו. Amar
Rava lo shanu ella shenasan l'rochvo.
That's only if you put, if you put this ארבע arba טפח
tefakh thing to the so you know the ארבע arba טפחים tefakhim
are going to the רוחב rochav width of the of the ditch,
meaning if you've got your ditch here, right, then these are and
these are then then the רוחב rochav the width here of the
ditch is the ארבע arba טפחים tefakhim width of the plank, okay.
That's נתן לרחבו. nasan l'rochvo. What's the alternative? אבל לאורכו אפילו כל
שהוא נמי שרי מעטיה מארבע. Aval l'orkho afilu kol shehu nami sharei
miyatei mei-arba.
If the whole ditch is only ארבע arba טפחים tefakhim from one
end to the other, right, the whole ditch is only ארבע arba
טפחים tefakhim from one end to the other, then rather than putting
it this way where this has to be ארבע arba טפחים tefakhim
wide, if you put it this way and it goes the entire
length of the ditch, then even if it's just an inch, it
makes the gap less than ארבע arba טפחים. tefakhim. Oh wow. Okay,
so rather than traversing the whole ditch, you can actually go the
length of the ditch set and make the gap less than ארבע
arba טפחים tefakhim and that would be enough. Now that raises interesting
questions because why does it have to go the whole length of
the ditch? What if, where's my pen?
Right? What if you've got here, I'm- you've got
right there's your
ditch, ארבע arba טפח, tefakh, right, but what would be if if
if like it jutted out here, okay, and at this point it
was שלוש shalosh טפח. tefakh. Okay. So would that maybe that should
be considered, maybe as long as you know who knows maybe if
it's ארבע arba טפחים tefakhim this little point that's jutting out or
something since you could go from one courtyard to the next, maybe
you should be able to make one עירוב eruv instead of two.
Right even though here and here you can't, but there's a point
that you can, it narrows and you could traverse. And if that's
true, then why when you put this plank down would you have
to put it down the entire length of the ditch, right? Why
would you have to put it down the entire length of the
ditch, of the courtyard? Why couldn't you just put this narrow plank
like that, right, and then you this this becomes a place where
you can cross over. So I don't exactly know the answer, maybe
it's because maybe the answer is that even if this was like
that, it wouldn't work. Maybe the answer is that since this natural
configuration is ארבע, arba, and this is an artificial extension, it has
to be the entire length, okay. But that's what it's saying that
if you want to put it the other way, then if even
a little bit. What? Oh, so that shows that that's exactly what
the גמרא's Gemara talking about.
I was going to the picture book.
Yeah, so that's,
so I'll tell you why I don't get this. So according to
this picture book, I was wondering, so this picture book, okay, it
says that that's actually exactly what the גמרא's Gemara saying, that the
גמרא's Gemara actually saying that if you put this plank here, okay,
then even in a little section if you make this part traversable,
right, then that actually works. But let me tell you why I
don't understand that. The reason I don't understand that is putting a
little plank here, right, it's a little bit, it's only one טפח,
tefach, right, presumably, I could be wrong about this too, but presumably
you need, as we've seen before when we talked about going like
crossing the wall and how big a doorway is, presumably this has
to be four טפחים tefachim wide, right? Okay, okay, and then you
do a little bit and it makes that point narrow and traversable.
If that's what the גמרא Gemara means, then I've got a question.
Then you would never need to do, assuming a plank, right, like
that, you'd never need to do it the other way, because every
plank like that is four טפחים tefachim wide, which we said a
plank has to be four טפחים tefachim wide, it never has to
get to the other end. It only has to be a little
bit. Now I guess the difference would be that if this gap
were more than four, this gap were like a hundred, you would
need to go the entire length. Okay, but again, I don't exactly
understand what is the scenario when the גמרא Gemara says, "Oh, if
you're going lengthwise then it's got to be four, but if you're
going widthwise it doesn't." Basically, it's another way of saying it doesn't
have to cross. As long as it goes a little bit and
there's one space that it's less than four, you're okay. Which might
be what the גמרא Gemara is saying, but it's a funny way
of saying it. All right, let's continue.
You notice you don't have any pictures over here, so this is
all academic.
Yeah, I know. Okay, okay. לכן שתי גזוזטראות זו כנגד זו. Lachen
shtei gezustraot zu keneged zu.
So if you've got two balconies facing one another. Now תוספות Tosafot
says, רש"י Rashi says this means you put a plank across them,
but תוספות Tosafot says all it means is, is that if there's
less than four טפחים tefachim from one balcony to the next, it's
considered like, like you know the, like a ditch less than four
טפחים tefachim where you can make one עירוב eiruv if you want.
Presumably these aren't high balconies, like some specifically, you know I've been
in apartments like that.
Yeah, right, right. Somehow it's easy to step from one to the
other.
Someone had to build a parapet if you did?
Yeah, that's true. But it could be that it's narrow enough that
you're not technically obligated. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, הא
דאמרת זו כנגד זו אין זו שלא כנגד זו לא. Ha de'amart
zu keneged zu in zu shelo keneged zu lo. First of all,
it's only if they're directly opposite one another. If one is here
and one is here, right, then even if there's only four, like
less than four טפחים tefachim between them, I'm reading it like תוספות,
Tosafot, right? How are you supposed to jump from one to the
other? That's not considered really accessible.
Okay. וזו למעלה מזו נמי. Vezu lemala mizu nami. And also if
one is here and they're like this, right, even if on the
horizontal there's less than four טפחים tefachim across, if they're different levels
it's also not considered accessible.
לא אמרן אלא שיש בין זה לזה שלושה טפחים. Lo amran ela
sheyesh bein zeh lezeh shelosha tefachim. That's true that they have to
be exactly at the same like, you know, vertical and horizontal for
this to work, only if there's, only if there is more than
שלושה shelosha between them. It's between three to 3.99.
אבל אין בין זה לזה שלושה. Aval ein bein zeh lezeh shelosha.
If there's less than three, גזוזטרא עקומה היא, Gezustra akuma hi, it's
just a bent balcony.
So basically what he's saying, I'm again
reading this תוספות's Tosafot way, okay, here you have your balcony out
here, right, here's your building or whatever, and here you've got the
other balcony out there, right? So we're saying that if it's less
than four, oops less than four, they're considered like the ditch less
than four and they're considered connected. So he says, "Ah, but that
means that if it's up here, right, or I don't know, somewhere
out out here, whatever, somewhere off to the side here, it's no
good if it's less than four, right? Even though it's less than
four it's no good because they're not considered connected, it's not easily
accessible." So he says, "That's only true if the gap is here
between three to 3.99."
Okay, that's when they're considered disconnected and it's not easily traversable. Okay,
that's when and therefore they're disconnected, not easily traversable, but if they're
opposite one another then that's okay. If they're higher than one another,
no good. But if the actual distance is less than שלושה, shelosha,
okay, the actual distance here although it would have to be like
pretty close because you'd probably go by, you know, not just the
horizontal distance but the actual distance traveled from one to the other,
if it's actually less than שלושה, shelosha, then it's, then they're considered
already connected. So even if it's not so easily traversable, like in
virtual reality, we consider it as if it's a bent balcony. I
don't know if I'm being clear or not. Let's try again. Look,
you've got these two balconies, right? So this is the way תוספות
Tosafot reads it. If it is four טפחים tefachim between them,
then
But that's only if they're directly opposite one another. If it's like
this, right? Or like this, right? Then even though less than four,
they're not considered traversable. So he says, yes, less than four they're
not traversable if you're talking about practically can you traverse it. But
if it's not just less than four, but actually less than three,
so it's like really close like this, even though it's less than
three, so in practice you can't step from one to the other,
but in halachic reality, it's less than three, then it's just then
anyway it's considered connected, it's considered לבוד. lavud. So that's all he's
saying. If the gap between them is less than three, where even
if it's not really traversable because they're at different heights or different,
you know, on the horizontal distance, but still לבוד lavud would make
them considered one. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues, now the next
משנה. mishna. And we just quoted this
before: מתבן שבין שתי חצרות, matben shebein shtei chatzerot, if you have
a huge, you know, sort of like wall of straw between two
courtyards, גבוה עשרה טפחים, gavoah asarah tefachim, and it's ten טפחים tefachim
high, מערבין שנים ואין מערבין אחד. me'arvin shnayim ve'ein me'arvin echad. So
again, it's a wall, so there's two separate courtyards you can't make
them one even if you want to. אלו מאכילין מכאן ואלו מאכילין
מכאן. eilu ma'achilin mikan ve'eilu ma'achilin mikan. Now, this is straw that
is not מוקצה. muktzah. This is straw, before we had spoken about
straw which is מוקצה, muktzah, that was straw which is going to
be used for making bricks and cement. This is straw that you
use to feed your animals, so it's not מוקצה. muktzah. So comes
שבת, Shabbos, you can start feeding your animal from this wall of
straw and each side of the courtyard can feed their respective animals,
assuming it's owned by both people.
Now, what's going to happen if you're feeding your animals with this
straw on שבת? Shabbos? It might get that the wall goes less
than ten טפחים tefachim on שבת. Shabbos. נתמעט התבן מעשרה טפחים, nitma'at
hateven me'asarah tefachim,
once it goes less than ten טפחים, tefachim, מערבין אחד ואין מערבין
שנים. me'arvin echad ve'ein me'arvin shnayim. Now you have to do one,
you don't have an option again, you're forced to do one courtyard.
The case where you can opt is you have a divider, you
have a wall or a ditch and you have a way to
traverse it. You have a wall with a door or a ditch
with a plank. But in the other cases, if you don't have
a wall that's ten טפחים tefachim or you don't have a ditch
that's ten טפחים tefachim deep, then by perforce it's all considered one.
So you're not talking about like a very, very wide מתבן, matben,
because then even if it's four, then you can, you know, do
what we're talking about, like...
No, the idea of stepping over, it's a good point, I said
it before. A wall, even if it's a very thin wall, is
a divider, whereas a ditch, if it's less than four טפחים, tefachim,
it's not wide, it's not a divider because you just step over
it.
But this מתבן... matben...
No, this מתבן matben is like a wall, so it doesn't matter
how wide it is. Do you notice it does not say that
it's wide? It just says it's ten high. אמר רב הונא, amar
Rav Huna, ובלבד שלא יתן לתוך קופתו ויאכיל. uvilvad shelo yiten letoch
kupato veyachil. So it's very nice you can feed your animal, but
you can't go ahead and bring your basket there and fill up
your basket. Why not? Because if we allow you to start filling
up your basket and then you're going to bring it back to
your house or your backyard where your animals are, then you might
very quickly reduce it from ten טפחים. tefachim. You won't be paying
attention, you'll be getting a large quantity, and you'll reduce it from
ten טפחים, tefachim, and if you do that on שבת Shabbos itself,
the גמרא Gemara is assuming that, no, well, it could have, it's
interesting, it doesn't assume סותר soter because it's all very temporary, but
the גמרא Gemara assumes that then you've made them one courtyard on
שבת Shabbos and you've lost your עירוב, eruv, because your עירובין eruvin
were separate, you didn't make a unified one.
Okay, so...
You're saying, but wait, we get into also other things, you're saying
that a halachic wall's not like a real, and for עירובין, eruvin,
it's not a halachic wall for שבת Shabbos for סתירה? stira?
Correct. And that's true. You can sometimes make a מחיצה mechitza on
שבת Shabbos which serves halachic purposes, although whatever, there's interesting questions about
that. But just because it serves as a halachic wall does not
mean that it's בונה boneh or סותר, soter,
although you are right sometimes it is in rigorous of בונה, boneh,
at least דרבנן. derabbanan.
Can you do two עירוב eruv to do one?
Oh, can you do a backup just in case? Presumably no. Presumably,
presumably if at the time you did the עירוב eruv they were
considered separate, you can't sort of make the עירוב eruv על תנאי.
al tenai. Yeah, it's an interesting question. But presumably no. But by
the same argument, why don't you say that the status it had
when שבת Shabbos began is the status that it remains? And we
often say that, that it works למקצת שבת. lemiktzat Shabbos. So we'll
get to that in a minute. Okay. So you can't fill it
up. Now why can't you fill it up? So one reason, the
simple reason is, of course, you'll come to make the wall too
small and it'll change the הלכה. halacha. But רש״י Rashi also suggests
a reason that it would be מוקצה. muktzah. Why would the grain
be מוקצה muktzah if you're feeding your animal the straw? So he
says it's מוקצה muktzah because it's designated as sort of like Michael
was saying, I mean, not because of a הלכה halacha of סותר,
soter, but more just your intention. You've intended it to serve as
a wall. And therefore that's as if in your mind you have,
you know, removed it from the role of animal fodder for שבת.
Shabbos. So I can't bring the animal there to eat? Well, right,
so because then you're not moving the מוקצה. muktzah. Alright, well let's
anyway, the first explanation is easier one, but we'll see in a
minute why רש״י Rashi says מוקצה muktzah because of the next גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says... שרי, sharei, and you're telling me
you could have your animal stand there and eat from it without
you actually putting it in your basket? דאמר רב הונא אמר רב
חיננא: De-amar Rav Huna amar Rav Chinana: מעמיד אדם את בהמתו על
גבי עשבים בשבת, Mamid adam et behemto al gabei asabim be-Shabbat,
you can have your animal, you know, make your animal stand, meaning
you sort of, you know, move your animal, not physically because your
animal's considered מוקצה, muktzeh, but you know, by walking behind your animal,
you get your animal to stand over grass and eat grass on
שבת, Shabbos, ואין מעמיד אדם את בהמתו על גבי מוקצה בשבת, ve-ein
mamid adam et behemto al gabei muktzeh be-Shabbat, and you can't have
him stand over and eat מוקצה. muktzeh. Why? We're afraid you'll pick
up the מוקצה muktzeh and feed it to him. Why wouldn't, I
mean, let's say you have, I don't know, some straw that's מוקצה,
muktzeh, okay, not like your pen, okay, some straw that's מוקצה, muktzeh,
we're afraid that you'll pick it up and eat it. Why aren't
we afraid you'll pick up the grass out of the ground? 'Cause
that's a דאורייתא, De-Oraisa, and we're not concerned that you'll forget to
do accidentally do a מלאכה דאורייתא. melachah De-Oraisa. But if it's just
מוקצה, muktzeh, and one could argue your animal's eating from it, which
also suggests מוקצה muktzeh has this taboo feeling like it's, you know,
it's sort of out of reach, here you're actively there as your
animal's eating from it sort of removes somewhat of the taboo aspect
of it and you might come and feed it to your animal.
So that's the story. So why is that a question? So the
question is if you're not allowed to yourself go and take from
this pile, either because it's מוקצה, muktzeh, which is why רש"י Rashi
says מוקצה muktzeh because it makes it exactly the same, or even
if the reason is just because we're afraid you're gonna too quickly
make it less than עשרה, ten, so you can't actively do it
yourself, why can you have your animal do it? It's only a
rabbinic issue, it's not a, right, and it's either מוקצה muktzeh or
some other rabbinic problem of maybe accidentally lowering the wall. So why
aren't we afraid that if you're there with your animal, you'll come
to do it yourself the same way we have that concern with
מוקצה? muktzeh? So the גמרא Gemara
says, where were we, דקאי לה
באפה ואזלה ואכלה. de-kaim lei be-apa ve-azla ve-achla.
No, we don't actually mean that you can stand there yourself with
the animal. That you wouldn't be allowed to do 'cause we're afraid
you would come to take the straw yourself. It means you can
sort of nudge your animal there. You stand in your animal's way
and you direct your animal till it goes there. But מאכילין, ma'achilim,
but you can't actually stand over it. So the גמרא Gemara is
sort of conceding the point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
ולא יתן לתוך קופתו תבן? ve-lo yiten le-toch kupato teven? And now
you say, now you can't put it directly into your basket? והתניא,
ve-ha tanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא: brayisa: בית שבין שתי
חצרות ומלאוהו תבן. Bayis she-bein shetei chatzeirot u-mle'uhu teven.
You have this house between two courtyards, so the house is basically
the gateway between one courtyard and the next, and what do you
do? You fill the house with straw. מערבין שנים ואין מערבין אחד.
Me'arvin shenayim ve-ein me'arvin echad.
So that's similar to the big pile of straw between the courtyards.
It's a wall, so you have to make separate עירובים. eruvs. ונוטל
לתוך קופתו ואוכל, ve-noten le-toch kupato ve-ochel, ונוטל לתוך קופתו ואוכל. ve-noten
le-toch kupato ve-ochel.
Now, you can go ahead, however, and fill from this wall straight
into your basket and then feed to your animal. So exactly the
opposite of what רב הונא Rav Huna said. רב הונא Rav Huna
says you cannot directly take from the wall into your basket and
here we're saying the ברייתא brayisa says you can take from this
wall into your basket. נסמט התבן מעשרה טפחים, Nismat ha-teven mi-asara tefachim,
now if the wall goes lower than עשרה טפחים, ten tefachim, שניהם
אסורים. shenehem asurin. Now presumably even on שבת Shabbos itself the הלכה
halachah changes and now they are both forbidden because you no longer
have a wall and you did not make one עירוב. eruv. כיצד
הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh?
Now, what are you gonna do if it's less than עשרה טפחים
ten tefachim and now we've got a problem? Now both courtyards are
forbidden, so how are we gonna fix the problem? נועל ביתו ומבטל
את רשותו. No'el beito u-mevatel et reshu-so.
So you lock your door, you basically, here's your, you know, here's
your three houses, right, house one, house two, whatever, back to the
drawing board,
right, house one, house two, house three, and these are the access
points and here you had this thing filled with this thing and
it was a wall and then because you were feeding from it
on שבת, Shabbos, now it's less than עשרה טפחים ten tefachim and
now we've got a problem because these two courtyards here became one.
So what do you do? So you basically, you're in this house
here, you're the צדיק, tzaddik, you want to help out courtyard B,
you're gonna slam this door here that connects into this house, you
lock your door, you're מבטל mevatel your רשות, reshus, we'll have to
ask why you need to be מבטל רשות, mevatel reshus, once you
lock your door you've made a wall, right, there's no way it
could be traversed, it's locked on that side, and therefore and now
your courtyard B is able to at least continue to use the
courtyard on שבת. Shabbos. We're gonna ask in a minute why you
also need ביטול רשות, bitul reshus, why locking the door isn't...
is that considered a בית שער beit shaar that the other house...
oh, let's not go there.
Okay, נועל ביתו ומבטל רשותו והוא אסור וחברו מותר. No'el beito u-mevatel
reshu-so ve-hu asur ve-chavero mutar. So you're forbidden because
you basically have made your thing a wall, but you cannot... Basically
you've been מבטל mevattel your entire rights to it because so we'll
the ביטול bittul as we know the guy who does the ביטול
bittul loses his rights and he can't take from his house into
the into the courtyard but it's a little unclear why he has
to do ביטול. bittul. So let's now וכן אתה אומר בגוב של
תבן שבין שני תחומי שבת vechen attah omer begov shel teven shebein
shene'i techumei shabbat
and similarly if you've got a
pile
of grain between two תחומים techumim basically the תחום techum of my
city my 2,000 אמה ammah here's my city remember the תחומים techumim
my 2,000 אמה ammah ends here and your 2,000 אמה ammah ends
here and there's this big pile of grain like that okay some
of it's in my תחום techum some of it's in your תחום
techum we're each allowed to take from the pile of grain but
we have to be careful not to reach over and take from
the other part of the pile which is outside of the תחום.
techum. קתני מיהת זה נותן לתוך קופתו וזה נותן לתוך קופתו
katani meihat zeh noten
letoch kuppato vezeh noten letoch kuppato
it's against what רב הונא Rav Huna said it says that you
can directly put into your basket so why is that if we're
shouldn't we be afraid that it'll become less than 10 and you
won't notice it? So אמרי amri you say here's the answer בית
כיון דאיכא תקרה כי מפחת מינכרא ליה
מילתא bayit keivan de'ika tikrah ki
mifchat minkara lei milta
no by a house you'll notice if the pile is getting low
how do you notice if the pile's getting low because the gap
between the top of the pile and the ceiling makes it more
noticeable that the pile is shrinking the whole concern of not filling
up your basket is you'll make the wall less than 10 without
noticing and you'll create a problem so by a house you'll notice
more you'll see the gap you'll see the gap between the top
of the grain and the ceiling growing whereas out in the field
you won't notice so much הכא לא מינכרא מילתא hacha lo minkara
milta if
you've got just a pile of straw out in the field and
it was 11 טפחים tefachim and now it's 10 and then it's
going to be 9 that small difference you won't notice because you
don't have that visual aid of the gap between it and the
ceiling yes
but isn't taking the straw from
the from the pile in the middle of the
תחומים techumim isn't there a carrying problem not as long as oh
in this case I assume your animal's right there and you're not
going more than four אמות ammot okay but we're not focusing on
that case we're focusing on the עירוב חצירות eruv chatzerot alright so
it says that because of the house you're allowed to go ahead
and do it and you will see if it gets less than
10 טפחים. tefachim. נפחת התבן מעשרה טפחים שניהם אסורים niphchat hateven me'asarah
tefachim sheneihem assurim
now we get to the point that the הלכה halachah can change
on שבת Shabbat itself whether you're allowed to or not allowed to
take directly if it actually happens that it gets less than 10
then it becomes a problem it becomes one courtyard that does not
have an עירוב. eruv. הא עשרה שרי ואף על גב דמדליא תקרה
טובא ha asarah shari ve'af al gav de'madlei tikrah tuva
it says one minute it says that if it's 10 you're still
okay even though the ceiling is very high meaning here you have
you have this house in the middle right and we're saying as
long as let's say that's a three-dimensional picture of a house and
as long as this pile of straw is 10 טפחים tefachim that's
considered a wall between these two houses but you might remember a
discussion about different units in an apartment building that we had a
while ago that said if the wall between the units even if
it's 10 טפחים tefachim high because it's a wall within a house
and they're all under the same ceiling right they're all considered to
be one in order to divide rooms in a house you need
the walls to get to the ceiling it's not enough to be
10 טפחים tefachim well that's exactly the same here you have these
connected houses and so what if you've got a pile of grain
here that's like a low divider in a house that doesn't separate
them that should not be so why does it work? So the
גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה נמי מחיצות שאין מגיעות לתקרה שמן מחיצות
shema mina nami mechitzot she'ein magiot latikrah sheman mechitzot does that mean
to suggest that if a מחיצה mechitzah that doesn't reach the wall
if you're indoors are effective didn't we say before that they're not
effective? So אמר אביי הכא בבית שלשה עשר חסר משהו עסקינן amar
Abaye hacha bevait sheloshah asar chasar mashehu askinan so really we're talking
that it's not much of a right it's not a you've got
to duck a lot the entire height of the מחיצה mechitzah is
thirteen and a bit off of the ground 13 טפחים tefachim which
is what like 40 inches the תבן teven is ten and the
grain is 10 so basically once the grain gets high enough to
be considered a מחיצה mechitzah 10 טפחים tefachim it actually just so
happens that the roof is very low and therefore it's less than
and the roof and the roof is like 12.99 off the ground
so the distance between the מחיצה mechitzah and the roof is less
than three and therefore it's considered לבוד lavud and it's as if
it reaches the roof okay pretty weak answer because clearly the simple
sense here is that 10 טפחים tefachim is enough and here we're
saying it has to be within three טפחים tefachim of the roof.
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר Rav Huna breide d'Rav Yehoshua amar
אפילו תימא afilu teima דביתי עשרה d'beiti asara ותבן שבעה ומשהו. v'teven
shiva umashehu. Then he says it could even be a shorter room.
Okay, it doesn't when it says the wall is 10, really no,
we're talking that the whole, the whole house is 10 טפחים tefachim
high, maybe it's really made more to store grain than it's made
to live in. The whole house is 10 טפחים tefachim high and
therefore if the grain is 7.1, then it's fine because then there's
less than three to the roof and it's like you have a
whole thing and it's like you have a wall of 10. Okay,
וכל פחות משלושה כלבוד דמי v'chol pachus mishlosha kilavud dami and that's
like לבוד lavud and therefore it works. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. בשלמא לאביי היינו דקתני מעשרה, bishlama l'Abaye haynu dikatani mi'asara,
from Abaye we says if it's less than 10 it's a problem.
אלא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מאי מעשרה? Ella l'Rav Huna breide
d'Rav Yehoshua mai mi'asara? Why does it say less than 10? For
him the whole pile to begin with is only 7.1. So the
גמרא Gemara says מתורת עשרה. mi'toras asara. It means it no longer
is effective as 10 because it, you know, it was 10 plus
the לבוד. lavud. So now and you lowered it so that it's
no longer 10 even with the לבוד. lavud. All right, but anyway
according to both of them, that deals with this issue, again the
simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is that the pile should be
enough, but based on an earlier discussion, we say that a low
divider or a divider that doesn't reach the ceiling indoors actually is
considered to be not a divider at all and therefore the גמרא
Gemara has to deal with this problem, even if that divider is
10 טפחים tefachim if it doesn't reach the ceiling. I should mention
there's an interesting תשובה, teshuvah, okay, here's something you weren't expecting, in
Rav Henkin that there's a lot of discussion in the פוסקים poskim
about the different status that an עזרת נשים ezras nashim has from
an עזרת ישראל, ezras Yisrael, the עזרת ישראל ezras Yisrael which is
what it's called in the מקדש, Mikdash, the עזרת גברים, ezras gevarim,
right, the men's section and the women's section, like there's questions of
various halachic questions about how much is it considered to be the
same קדושה, kedusha, different קדושות, kedushas, less holy to put not too
fine a point on it, right, that's the question, that's the question
in various פוסקים. poskim. So Rav Henkin says that was only when
it was literally a separate room or when the divider went up
to the ceiling. And if you know, there's some שולס shuls that
that's the way it is, it goes all the way and it's
tiny little things. He says but as soon as the מחיצה mechitza
doesn't get up to the ceiling, then it's all considered to be
one room anyway and not all of those discussions become moot. So
that's very interesting how that's very basically based on, you know, discussions
such as this, that a divider even if it's 10 טפחים, tefachim,
if it doesn't reach the ceiling, does not really consider to make
those as separate domains.
Can you take from this if you want to expand
the women's...
right, so Rav Henkin would say that all those discussions are moot
if you're dealing with if the divider doesn't get up to the
ceiling. Okay, so just so it was an interesting practical application of
some of this.
He's not necessarily accepted because the usual הלכה halacha is you can't...
I understand, but he is correct that most of those תשובות teshuvot
were written when women's sections were actually separate rooms. That's a huge
issue right now. I understand, okay, I'm just saying that that's his
take. Right. Right, a temporary barrier, no permanence. Right, right. So that,
right, you are correct, obviously there are those that would not
agree with that. Yes. Is women's section less holy than men's?
All right, I knew I should have brought it up. Not everybody
says that. Not everyone says it. But there are...
it gets to the whole issue of תפילה בציבור tefilla b'tzibbur is
defined by the men and so on. So it comes up when
the question is can you reconfigure a synagogue so something that was
once the men's section is now the women's section? And some פוסקים
poskim say no because that's lowering its קדושה kedusha because of... I
know, you should be offended. You should be offended. But I'm saying
right, but I just... I was a little reluctant to bring it
up for that reason. Shall I give you some more worms right
now? Thankfully, thankfully not all the פוסקים poskim say that. There're definitely
פוסקים poskim that completely reject that and say they have the same
קדושה. kedusha. But Rav Henkin is saying that even those that say
that it has different, it would be moot if the divider did
not reach the ceiling and mostly they were talking when the divider
reached the ceiling. That's his argument. Yes. At the new synagogue at
Einstein, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, which was opened a couple years
ago, they had the men on the left, the women on the
right. And then about three months later they switched to have the
women on the left
and the men on the right. Okay, and nobody complained. And then
three months later they switched it back to the original configuration. Very
nice. So, very... Oh, I went to the wrong... Okay, we got
to move guys, we're getting at least to the next משנה. Mishnah.
שנים אסורים. shnayim asurim. So when it falls down, when it's lower
than 10, they become אסור assur even though it changed on שבת.
Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה דיורין הבאין בשבת אסורין.
shma mina d'yorin habaim b'Shabbos asurin. So you see that when guests
come on שבת, Shabbos, not guests like new dwellers, it's אסור, assur,
meaning that something that was an עירוב eruv when שבת Shabbos began
can lose its status when things change on שבת Shabbos itself. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא דאטמיט מעצמו.
dilma d'itmait me'atzmo.
No, maybe it didn't mean that happened on שבת. Shabbos. Maybe you're
right, maybe if on שבת Shabbos itself the pile went down below
10, it wouldn't be a problem. problem this שבת Shabbos because this
שבת Shabbos you started okay. But it means next שבת Shabbos you're
going to have a problem now that you don't have a wall.
Of course, if that were true, why are we so anxious that
you might come to make it less than
ten and not notice if הלכה halachically at least this שבת Shabbos
you're still good? Unless the point is you won't notice and then
it even until next week you won't notice. But this is the
גמרא's Gemara question, will
it actually change on שבת Shabbos
itself and it says not necessarily. Maybe it means next שבת Shabbos
it'll be a problem.
You're not supposed to measure on שבת Shabbos anyway, right? No you
can measure, you can measure, you can measure for הלכה halachic purposes
actually. So yeah, so you're allowed, in theory you'd be allowed, but
that's the question whether it actually changes the הלכה halacha on שבת
Shabbos itself. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? Now, if you do
have this thing that it's no longer a wall, what are you
going to do? נועל ביתו ומבטל רשותו. No'el beiso umivatel reshuso. You
lock up your house and you're מבטל mivatel your רשות reshus because
presumably now when it opened up, all of this was considered one
courtyard. Right? So we've got a problem, right? Because here you had,
right, you know, you had these courtyards and this wall went down
below ten, let's say on שבת Shabbos itself, okay, so therefore, and
this is all open space, this was the only divider. Now they're
all considered one courtyard, okay? What are you going to do? So
and they didn't make one עירוב. eiruv. So if they didn't make
one עירוב, eiruv, you've got to do ביטול רשות, bitul reshus, right?
So you could, he says, you lock the door, so you essentially
make that as a wall, okay, and you've now got I guess
you would have to actually say, anyway, and now you do the
ביטול רשות bitul reshus so that it's all the, everybody who lives
here loses their rights and it's all and everybody there has a
right, has a right to use it. So you do the two
things. I'm just trying to figure this out because I'm not getting
it. Because if this is a wall here, then at most this
should be, oh you know what we'd have to say? You'd have
to say that this is a wall and that this is probably
like ten אמות amos wide I'm guessing. Because and therefore once it
goes down, so therefore when it goes down they're necessarily one and
when it's up they're necessarily two. But if it was less than
ten אמות amos wide, then you would always have the option of
being separate. Okay, anyway, so what you do is you lock this,
you make it back into a door and then you do the
ביטול, bitul, oh but you became part of that courtyard so you
do ביטול. bitul. So the גמרא Gemara says, who needs both? Let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says תרתי, tarti, both? Either
normally ביטול bitul works as we know, if some of the people
of the courtyard didn't participate, which effectively this is now, or locking
the door should work at least if you did it on שבת
Shabbos before שבת Shabbos began, if that was what we were talking
about, then it totally reverses the problem of the of the of
the fact that the wall fell down. So הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
או נועל ביתו או מבטל רשותו. o no'el beiso o mivatel reshuso.
Okay, it means one or the other. Okay, you do either ביטול
bitul or you lock the door. Presumably locking the door I imagine
would only help ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, right? Because on שבת Shabbos
itself you normally would not, that's normally not a solution. Once you
have one courtyard, you know, it normally would not be a solution
to change it in the middle of שבת Shabbos other than by
doing ביטול. bitul. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, if you want you could
say לעולם תרתי. le'olam tarti. It really you need both. כיון דדש
בה אתי לטלטולי. keivan dedash bah asi letaltulei. Since you are trampled
there, you'll come to carry. So what does that mean? So רש"י
Rashi says, it's for the היכרא. heikera. You need a but in
which case? So the גמרא Gemara says, so the way רש"י Rashi
explains it is, look, in order for the people here in courtyard
B to use their courtyard, it's enough that you basically locked the
door or it's enough that you did ביטול. bitul. Okay, but we've
got a problem. Since it would be very common for you to
go from one courtyard to the next, what you require for yourself
to be a היכרא heikera that you don't come to accidentally, you
know, carry in B is in addition to doing ביטול bitul you
have to lock your door. And therefore רש"י Rashi says, that's actually
always true, says רש"י, Rashi, that after you do even if you
do ביטול, bitul, since it's common for you to take from your
house into the courtyard, in order to remind yourself you would have
to actually lock the door. And תוספות Tosafos points out an earlier
גמרא Gemara you might remember when something fell down on שבת Shabbos
and רב Rav said, oh take all my stuff to the back
room because he was afraid he might accidentally come out. So according
to רש"י, Rashi, it's for your sake that you don't accidentally take
out. The courtyard is fine with ביטול, bitul, you need to lock
your door. תוספות Tosafos says, what are you supposed to do, stay
in a locked house the whole שבת? Shabbos? So תוספות Tosafos says,
okay, maybe when you leave you go out and you lock it
behind you, but when you come in, you also lock it. So
as long as you're in the house you have to lock your
door so you what? Say that part again. When you leave your
house, you lock your door, and when you come back in, you
lock your door. It's not that you have to be caged all
שבת. Shabbos. But when you're in the house you have to lock
it so you don't accidentally carry. That's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות
Tosafos doesn't like that explanation and תוספות Tosafos says no, no, no.
This is because in this one case, normally you're totally allowed, something
accidental happened that the pile of grain got less, you're going to
forget about you know you're not going to sort of have that
in mind and therefore here you need to do a double thing.
And it's only, תוספות Tosfos says, for just one שבת. Shabbos. By
next שבת Shabbos you'll have it fixed. So this type of a
thing that it was a one-time thing that you might accidentally do
it wrong because you never it's never this way, you have to
do something a double type of a thing but normally not. Okay,
let's keep up let's go to the משנה. Mishnah. אם הוא עשה
לחבירו מותר. Im hu asa l'chaveiro mutar. פשיטא. Pshita. Obviously when if
it works based on ביטול, bittul, right it's not obvious if it's
based on the door, but if it works based on ביטול bittul
וההלכה היא ביטול ve'hahalachah hi bittul is you give up your rights
and the other one has his rights. לא צריכא דהדר איהו ובטיל
ליה לחבריה. Lo tzricha d'hadar ihu u'batil lei l'chavrei. No, what we're
talking about is that's the way it remains, even if he tried
to reverse the favor and now be מבטל mevatel the courtyard back
to you. והא קמשמע לן דאין מבטלין וחוזרין ומבטלין. V'ha kamashma lan
d'ein mevatlin v'chozrin u'mevatlin. Remember that was a discussion, can you take
turns who's doing ביטול bittul to whom? So here the point is,
no, this is the way it remains. You did ביטול, bittul, that's
the way it is for the rest of שבת, Shabbos, he cannot
reverse the favor. But isn't it ביטול מחצר לחצר bittul me'chatzer l'chatzer
issues? That's a good question. That's an interesting question. If the thing
is that it's when it went down from before שבת Shabbos it's
not or if the point is that they're one and not two
then it's not מחצר לחצר me'chatzer l'chatzer now it's defined as one
חצר. chatzer. But it's a good point. Right? It's not like you
have an option of two or one. It is one, that's why
it's a problem. וכן אתה אומר בגו של תבן שבין שתי תחומי
שבת. V'chein ata omer b'gov shel teven she'bein shtei tchumei Shabbos. Similarly
if you've got this big thing of grain between two תחומין tchumin
then you can take from each side can take from their side
but you have to be careful not to take from the other
side. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. Pshita. Obviously. לא צריכא לרבי
עקיבא דאמר תחומין דאורייתא. Lo tzricha l'Rabbi Akiva d'amar tchumin d'oraisa. It's
needed for Rabbi Akiva that says תחומין tchumin is a biblical issue.
מהו דתימא ליגזר דלמא אתי לאחלופי. Mah d'teima ligzar dilma ati l'achlufei.
Maybe according to Rabbi Akiva because it's a biblical concern I shouldn't
even let you feed off of your side of it because you'll
come to biblically transgress תחומין tchumin by taking grain from the other
side. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that we are not concerned with that.
Okay so to be continued tomorrow we will pick up from the
משנה. Mishnah. Oh excuse me. See isn't there a משנה מצבת שבין
שתי חצירות Mishnah matzeives she'bein shtei chatzeiros right? And then it's מערבין
שתיים. me'arvin shtayim. Yeah because they're two חצירות. chatzeiros. Right but it's
but the whole problem is when the מצבת matzeives goes down. When
the מצבת matzeives goes down.